so
meditate go to your breath tie your mind
to your breath there's no other thing in
the
world except your breath just your
breath there's nothing else in the
world
e
e e
come to that golden room room covered
with sunlight
look at the blue of the sky at the
window e
look at the mountains across the
valley e
come back to the Golden
Moon and see your heart teacher in front
of
you and feel them take your hand
and just concentrate on the touch of
their
hand you might even close your eyes in
your med in the golden
room
e
e e
try to see what kind of problems come up
in your meditation are you thinking of
something
else maybe something you have to do
someone you have to talk to
later or are you spacing
out getting
sleepy or maybe the object is not that
fascinating
to no
more try to call up a sense of
satisfaction and willingness to stay
there
without moving just the hands
touching and
a a feeling of well-being willingness
to happy to stay silent
unmoving together with your
hearted
e
e e
slowly come back to this
L open your
eyes I used to sort diamonds uh in the
diamond business that's what should do
and in a large company you have long
long
tables and uh many tensor lights and
then you have special paper made in
Belgium so you can toss diamonds on them
and they they land the right way and
then uh the chairs have all their legs
cut off so you're up straight your back
is straight and you're you're got the
eye thing and you're going like this and
then
uh you might do a th Stones an hour or
something like that uh but but they
start you on five or something like that
they say do five Stones well in an hour
you're okay so when you first get there
you just do five Stones an hour and your
shoulder feels like it's on fire because
it's up like this all day and you have
horrible pains in your body and then uh
your body
adjusts and then they they take you up
to 10 stones an hour something like that
um but there's a big emphasis on you
don't go faster
until until you're perfect you see what
I mean so you can't go to 10 stones an
hour until you do five Stones an hour
without a
mistake uh and I think you're starting
to sense that meditation would be good
done that way so uh three or four
minutes of really good
meditation is better than a half hour of
subtle dullness subtle dullness is
pernicious it becomes a habit very
quickly and then you get satisfied with
it and you never progress you know so
there's two kinds of people you meet one
says I tried to meditate and I couldn't
what you called I tried to meditate and
I gave up I quit and then you find other
people you say I I tried to meditate but
nothing's happening I I meditate every
day and nothing's happening you know I
don't seem to change and my meditation
doesn't seem to change so there's
two categories of people I think the
second category is sad you know I'd
rather have given it up than to do it
poorly year after year and and feel like
I'm not getting anywhere so in the
diamond business they require quality
before speed and if you try to do speed
and don't have quality they fire you
because that means the person's never
going to they're going to keep rushing
and making errors that other people have
to fix so they rather have somebody slow
that does a good job cuz then they'll
pick up speed and they'll they'll always
be good but if someone's impatient and
they keep making errors because they're
trying to go too fast then they just get
rid of them because you can't fix those
people you see so better to do a few
minutes of very high quality
concentration and then break and do
something else for a while like study
the greatest book on emptiness and then
uh go back and do some more and you will
build up quickly if it's high quality it
will build up quickly if it's poor
quality it won't it won't change even
the time won't
change okay so we're going to do some
emptiness
stuff
uh uh we're picking off where we left
off picking up where we left off
so there is a llama named ketang
sometimes it's called
Kang uh we don't know his dates exactly
probably 300 years ago a k his name was
jamyang mlam and he used to say that uh
whatever
object you took in the world
uh it would have as much gaka about it
as the collection of its parts so let me
talk about that
um you have to know uh there's a
distinction it's called DOI
do and do
and so you should I let you talk that
much yeah it's probably good see okay
you ready you can say it okay
[Music]
one so these are
three parts of
a of everything
okay
dshi means all the stuff together that
you're going to conceptualize in a
certain way so all the parts of the
car uh as a whole all the parts of the
car assembled together as a ho is the
daki meaning the thing you're going to
think of as something okay the thing
you're going to think of as something
it's the top of the pen and the bottom
of the pen and the tube of the pen and
the barrel of the t pen all put together
but it hasn't been thought of as a pen
yet that's daki all the parts together
before you think of it as a pen before
your mind forces you to think of it as a
pen okay that's
D do do same verb different tense okay
uh
different
call paiser activiz we don't have it in
English so doj means the the state of
mind which synthesizes those parts into
a thing okay do it's called doj your
your mind under the influence of your
karmic seeds right under the influence
of your kic seed your mind organizes
those parts and and decides it's a
certain thing called a pen or called a
Cho
okay that's called
do means the result of that process
which is which is the pen a pen which
has been synthesized out of the parts of
a pen okay so pen is the synthesized
object the finished object which has
been synthesized by a mind
influenced by its karmic seeds
interpreting a number of parts in a
certain way interpreting collection
Parts in a certain way and coming up
with a thing which could have been a
Choy if you'd had different
seeds Okay so so the collection of Parts
is is so kind of
neutral and then the the doj the the
doing mind the mind which is synthesizes
a thing out of it uh due to the seeds in
its own in your own heart decides to see
it as a pen or decides to see it as a
chew toy by the way that determines your
rebirth there's no such thing as rebirth
there are no dog body factories in
Kansas somewhere where they turn out dog
bodies with little holes in the back and
stuff Spirits into them okay it's just
that your karmic seeds
shift and you're seeing the same
collection of Parts as a chah
that means you is a
dog got it and that's that's all rebirth
is it's weird okay so it's not that you
go anywhere else and it's not that they
put you in any other body those are
lower interpretations of rebirth that
your soul goes into a new body or
something like that it's not it's not
true uh different seeds assert
themselves and you say the same
collections of Parts as different
objects
okay and and that applies to this also
you see these five digits as a
paw they're still the same as they were
before they haven't changed they were no
more a hand than they are now a Paul it
was the seeds in your own mind that made
you see them as a hand and now it's the
seeds in your own mind that makes you
see them as a paw they don't
change okay it's it's scary it means
rebirth is feasible rebirth as a dog is
Fe
and it takes the amount of time that it
takes to season your mind to reassert
themselves which is about 165 of a
second okay you can become a dog you can
get hit by a car and become a dog within
165th of a second because because it's
coming from your
mind just new seeds assert themselves
and and you see a paw instead of a hand
in the same place as the hand was okay
and that's how fast it takes to be
reborn forget this thing about you know
you you have to look for a dog body and
you have to go there and it's all lower
school okay higher school
is within 10 seconds after a car
accident you can be a dog because it's
just a change in perception okay all
right so jamyang mlam this llama from
1700s said uh
[Music]
how big is the gaka with every different
thing it's as big as the collection of
its parts okay that's where we started
out saying right uh take all the parts
of the pen take it together and that's
how big the gcha will be it will be
limited to the edge of that
object so the extent of the gcha is
equal to the extent of the all the stuff
of the thing put
together okay so if the if you put
together pen and it's 1 in thick the
gaka corresponding to that is 1 in thick
okay like that uh the gaka will always
be as big or as little as the thing as
the collection of the parts of the thing
are joined together uh he's getting into
a nice
Point that's the ultimate object that we
deny with our use of of of reason
okay through reasoning we we decide that
that thing doesn't
exist the word ultimate would seem to be
a MinGa which means you can't answer but
uh it would it would imply that there
are lesser
doctors which are not the the the
one there's one non-existent thing that
if you cancel it you can save the world
and there are other lesser wrong ideas
that if you cancel them you just save
your emotions or something okay the
ultimate gaka is it's important to say
ultimate gaka
okay there's a famous word in called
which
means it's really hard to translate it
means
the maybe you could say the feel of the
object okay the feel of the object uh
with a
pen uh it would be
uh with a pen it would be the the
feeling that it's coming from the pen
all right so that's another name for
gaka okay the feel of the feel of the
thing the wrong feel of the thing
okay of our tendency to see things as
real
if we can't identify
the wrong feeling we have about a pen
that is coming from itself okay if you
can't isolate that
feeling and get used to
it okay which is the gaka the the
feeling that it's coming from its own
sign you have it automatically when I
lift it up when I lift it up you have a
feeling that it's coming from itself
okay if you can isolate that feeling
from your perception of the
pen the pen
exists the the feel feeling that it's
coming from itself that
that appearance that that is detected by
that feeling is doesn't exist okay at
the same moment with a pen you're having
two two feelings are coming up in you
one is that it's a pen that's okay
that's correct it is a pen and you can
write with it but mixed in with that
feeling like water and milk as
indistinguishable as water and milk is
another feeling that is coming from
itself
okay and to separate them is the is our
goal it's and a lot of people have
failed and then they said pens don't
exist so that's wrong you can write with
a pen so the the the sensation or the
feeling that it's a writing tool is
correct the the the concomittant or
the the feeling that always comes along
with that that it's a pen from its own
side is is totally wrong and what that's
believing in is the gaka okay okay got
it at the same time you're always having
two subtle perceptions one that it's
what it is which is okay and the other
is that what it it's what it is from its
own sign and that's not okay and to
isolate the second one from the first
one is a very difficult task because you
might overdo it and say there's no pens
or you might underdo it and say it's a
pen from its own side okay it's very
subtle
your mind is part of your mind is always
making a
mistake part of your mind is okay it's a
pen okay and to separate those two is
difficult
uh then people come up with this thing
called dender dender means real okay the
word dend means
real then he goes off on this thing
about emptiness literature terminology
okay emptiness literature lingo for
example uh
real or cancel the
real uh or
self-standing or
true or real he says if you get
you can start thinking of those terms
and self-existent ways themselves okay
that's a difficulty you start throwing
around words from majima you start
throwing around emptiness study
terminology and then you get used to
those words and you don't know what they
apply to you just start like the word
self-existent in English the people
throw around the word self-existent a
lot but they've never really taken an
object and tried to isolate what what it
is to think it's self-existent they just
say don't think of the pen is
self-existent they don't they don't have
a personal experience of what it is to
be self-existent okay so he's warning us
against
uh against getting stuck on the
terminology okay and not experiencing
what it refers to okay
just be a person who just keeps
repeating philosophical terms you know
oh it's not like like all the hundreds
of Dharma students who keep talking
about self-existent but if you ask them
what is self-existent they can't really
describe it it's you hold up the pen and
the pen seems to come from its own side
that's self-existence okay so you have
to learn to isolate that part of your
perception of a pen from the perception
that it's a writing instrument which is
correct okay
iming you can turn around words like
self-existent or not real or no self-
nature what anatman right you can throw
around those terms but if you if you
can't just hold up a pen and and
describe it in two
seconds
then then you can't stop the tendency to
think it's coming from its own side okay
use
terminology like self not self-existent
or no self or
unman and then not being able to
describe what it is with a pen in about
two seconds is not going to do any
damage to your tendency of holding it
the wrong way which is why you live in a
world where things don't work or only
work sometimes as long as you still have
that tendency to think that they're
working from their own
side uh you will
suffer and they won't work uh and you
can't damage that tendency if you keep
throwing around words like self-existent
and you can't even describe it with a
pen okay with a simple object you can't
describe what it means to be
self-existent okay
then if you keep proceeding that
way you won't be able the you won't come
down to the right gaka you won't get
down to the
righta you'll start making up new
gas no you go to a lecture by his
Holiness I I've watched thousands of
people do that and and the translator is
talking self existent all all afternoon
and everyone's nodding you know and and
then
uh they hear the word self-existent and
then they try to imagine what it refers
to right or they say no
self I I was I had a terrible moment in
uh where was
it
Pana in Gujarat State it's a it's a Holy
Mountain to the James and uh I was
trying to get funding for acip which is
my constant PR movement around the world
and
uh and uh I heard there was this Jane
Saint I I met a diamond dealer I said
would you help us he said I'll give you
a million dollars I said that's good and
then uh he said but I said what do you
mean but he said my Guru has to approve
it I said well who's your Guru you know
and he said this is a Swami Jambu or
something and I said okay well let's
call him and he says no no you don't
understand he's a Wandering Jane Saint
he's
a he's a naked
Saint and he wanders around India with a
broom uh and so I said well how are we
going to give us permission where is he
right now he says how do I know you know
and then and then I'm like uh he says
but every year at the at the poana
festival Jane Festival he he's at the
top of the mountain he walks to the top
of the mountain Barefoot over this
gravel you know like 10 Mi or something
and you can meet him there you know so I
figure well million
dollars I I fly to n and and then I
here's another town
and I forget the name of it anyway soay
I fly there on this rickety plane I get
out I take a long car
drive uh and then I take off my shoes
and I walk up this
I almost said a bad word uh mountain and
my my feet are bleeding by the time I
get to the top because you're not
allowed to go up the mountain with shoes
on and then I meet Swami diur you know
and and he's
like so I explained the situation to him
you know and he says I understand I
understand he says you know I I have
quite an understanding of Buddhist
philosophy he was at 95 or something you
know and and I'm like okay
and he says uh I but I can't approve the
million dollars and I said why and he
says n it's all the garina you know and
I was like what's wrong with the gina he
says you know as well as I do that Nina
said nothing
exists you
know like this was a fight that went on
two 1,800 years ago you know and he's
he's bringing it up again you know no
it's the same players I'm the I'm the
Buddhist and he's the Jane you know and
I'm like that's what not what n meant
you know and he said said yes yes I've
read the text the guardian said nothing
exist you know I said no he just said
there doesn't exist anything which
doesn't come from Cara I just said it
that and then he looks at me and he
goes we can accept
that so I'm like will you give me a
million dollar he says
Nope uh let's buy cows and and liberate
cows with I'll take the million dollars
but we'll buy cow and we'll liberate
cows so
anyway uh why did I bring that
up
busted oh yeah that's where we were yeah
so people hear this non see yeah that
you were right um uh people hear
self-existent right they hear Nar say
self-existent no self they hear Nar say
no self and for 18 centuries and then or
they're sitting in a a talk by his
Holiness and they hear no self and then
they start making up this weird GTA in
their head you know
like like cars that aren't cars or pens
that aren't pens you know or or or
everything's kind of aery and you could
put your hand through it somehow and you
know like everything's Phantoms or
something like that you know they start
getting really weird G in their mind
because because the word no self makes
them think you know they think there's
no me no self can apply to things right
no self means the book is you should
have called it the thing is not
itself that's more correct translation
you know the book is not itself and then
you have to explain it right
so what he's talking about here he says
people hear words people hear
terminology like no
s then they make up some uh new kind
of and then their whole view of these
questions becomes also made
up they make up the gaka they make up a
new gaka like no car exists it's some
kind of fantas
Miracle Car that you could put your hand
through everything's an illusion and
then based on that misperception they
make up whole new wrong schools of
philosophy you know and they say oh
Buddhists don't believe in anything or
Buddhists don't believe that cars are
cars or something like that okay listen
D to put it briefly
jet jet
who's jeten lo you can't
answer yeah she said first p a
llama okay first punch in
llama but his name's not Chen it's
Chon so anyway that's an abbreviation
those of you are studying tobet they
don't call him first pension Lama they
call him first pen or pen LA or
something like then you have to know
that means loan he said he's our hero
right he's the dam writer he wrote the
lopa that we did last night uh that
beautiful thing he's he's amazing he's
the guy who walked out between two
armies that were about to start a you
know third Tibetan world war and talked
them out of fighting with each other and
paid them off P God he arranged for
people to pay each each side off so they
wouldn't fight with each other so
therefore he for 92 years you know in a
world where people live to 40
anyway he
said very beautiful very important thing
here okay Rak means Dak means R means
here's the first pension Lama maybe the
greatest writer in the history of Tibet
greatest poet Maybe
and he's saying all of us
Schmucks like he's throwing himself in
with us okay all us all us
guys we keep looking for AA which is
something other than the way everything
around us is constantly appearing to us
in the first
place got it we keep looking for a gaka
which is something different than the
way everything around us is appearing to
us all the
time okay like we keep trying to find
some philosophical gaka when it's it in
fact it's the way that everything is
appearing to us all the time all right
everything you don't have to go look for
some gcha just look cuz you're doing it
all the time you're always
misinterpreting everything the gaka is
appearing to you every minute of every
day with every single stripe on her
blouse and every single hair and his
head and and the and the building and
the world and and all the thoughts
running through your mind everything
that appears to you is appearing in the
wrong way and you take it that way okay
if you want a gaka says the first
pension Lama I
mean just look at
your
just just look in front of you it's
there all right all the time you don't
have to make up some gotcha with some
philosophical school okay
uh this is very important okay very very
very important what's a
so it's a non okay anybody who has not
seen emptiness directly people always
coming up to me gu I think I saw
emptiness just stop right there okay if
you think you're wrong okay you didn't
they're going to ask me did I see
emptiness directly you know and I'm like
if you're asking me you didn't okay Lou
Armstrong what' they say some guy went
up to him said what's Jazz Louis
Armstrong he says man if you got to ask
you'll never know you know so
uh it's the same with direct perception
EMP if you think you had one you didn't
all right so anyway anyone who hasn't
seen emptiness directly so Gula she all
states of Mind of any person who has not
seen emptiness Direct
are Le are infected with ignorance all
the time okay every perception you've
ever had in your life if you haven't
seen emptiness
directly was tainted okay and was was
wrong was somehow wrong okay what was it
wrong about this being a
pen no was it wrong about the feeling
that the pen was coming from the pen
which always compies the perception dep
that it was wrong about okay that'sa
that's
Thea means your every perception of a
nonya in the universe is always infected
by a mistaken State of Mind okay because
there's always this feeling that the
thing's coming from its own side when in
fact it's
not and that feeling is what makes us
suffer because then we believe that the
things coming from from it and not from
us if we understood it was coming from
us we could change it but but since we
think it's coming from its own side we
put up with pens that run out of
me you know we buy 10 and we hope that
all of them work and we keep getting
more off the shelf I have a Shelf at
home I have 20 of these pens there my
friends steal them all the time they
come up with this
Japanese what's it
called anyway yeah Leen Japanese Leen I
was like how many people have a Japanese
Tokyo
lepen all my friends have them I'm like
where' you get
that like I go to Great Lengths to get
them because I can write I can translate
fast with them you know but
anyway
uh why did I talk about oh yeah so it's
always a a sensation or a feeling that
the Pen's coming from its own side
right and that causes all our suffering
that that adulterated perception of the
pen the adulteration part is what causes
all our
suffering causes death itself
uh and due to that infection of our
senses uh everything is appearing to us
the wrong
way as the first pension has
said to us normal people
right us normal
people
doc whether we're talking about me pumo
whether they're talking about my body
and mind rwa whether we're talking about
the
mountains K whether we're talking about
the buildings Kim whether we're talking
about the homes
Etc
CH every object in your world every
single object in your world okay from
houses to people to
everything there's a
there's a
okay uh conventional appearance to it
it's a pen and then there's a not okay
feeling that it's coming from
itself okay and they are always uh what
do you call it they're always melted
together they're always
uh shs now you can't give me
words you can just think them and send
it to me okay they're always uh mixed up
like a water and milk why do they say
water and milk once you pour milk into
water try to unseparate I mean try sorry
try to separate the water from the milk
afterwards like could you take the milk
out of the water please you know and
it's it's almost
impossible to
separate the correct perception that
it's a pen from the incorrect feeling
that it's coming from itself is very
difficult and every perception you have
is infected by the second you see they
are
they're always mixed with each other
like milk and water and to try to divide
them is very difficult
okay so from the object's point of view
unfortunately you can't say the top of
the pen is appearing to me to come from
its own side but the base of the pen is
not it would be easier right life would
be easier you just throw out the tops
you know but he says
unfortunately not only do you make this
mistake with every object you make this
mistake with every detail of every
object okay it's not like the wheels of
the car are exempt from you thinking
they come from their own side and the
top of the car is not exempt from you
thinking it's coming okay you think
every part of everything coming from its
own side so the problem is not just that
you take everything around you to be
coming from its own side
you take every part of everything around
you you don't get a break all
right so you never have anything in the
whole world in your life that appears to
you without being infected by that idea
or that feeling that is coming from its
own
side I think we should do a little
meditation let me think
uh oh maybe one more sentence uh
R so you don't have to go to any big
philosophy text and try to you know look
up all these weird names like
self-existent and you know you go to a
diama Lector you know the conventional
reality of the consisting subobject of
the you know and you're
like whoa you know I wish I knew what
they were talking
about but everything you're listening to
everything you're looking at and the
seat you're sitting in you're having
that feeling about them so you don't
have to worry about the lecture just
think about the seat you're sitting in
and that's appearing to you as
self-existent okay cuz you think it
comes from its own sight that's what
he's saying he's saying just just try to
get in touch with with the gas right
around you all the time and don't worry
too much about these big book okay and
then you've covered the book okay all
right then he wants to talk about those
people who fatigue themselves by trying
to find some other gaka okay instead of
just taking the ones that are right
around them they go off to some
philosophical camp and you know try to
isolate some exotic
GTA okay with a pen that's that's the
gaka on a table that's the gaka sitting
in on their butt that's a gcha okay all
right I mean and they're they're pouring
through the books looking for the GTA
you know and the fingers they're using
to turn the pages on of gaka okay got it
all right let's
meditate watch your
B e
go to the golden
room you can rest there you can take
your rest there it's
quiet you don't have anything to do
relax
enjoy the
light late late afternoon early evening
look at the sky enjoy the
sky
blue infinite
look across the valley to the
mountain e
come back to the golden
room feel the sunlight warm on your
knees THS
and ask your heart teacher to come and
sit with
me try very hard you can cut through
agitation you can cut through dullness
if you go straight to
Nar try very hard to just enjoy sitting
quietly with your teacher if you can get
to that enjoyment or that
contentment you will have overcome
agitation and
dullness in one in one swoop
be
contented be at
peace enjoy the
silence and just be with your
teacher be aware of the warmth of their
body make that your object for this
session the warmth emanating from their
body on the front of your
body e
if you go off the object of the warmth
of your teach
body then try to
examine what's the typical way you go
off is it that you think about a meal
coming up or you think about uh what's
going to happen after the to
or are you uh think plan plans about
next
week there will be a pattern and then
you can work on that pattern you
can put your watchfulness to watchful
for what's typical for you or are you
losing your enjoyment of the
object or are you just feeling
tired what what's the typical way that
you lose the object
try to go back to the enjoyment stay
with the
enjoyment contentment of The Quiet of
the golden
room e
take your sustenance from that quiet
then come back slowly to this
room then relax and open
your uh we'll close with one more
beautiful this is a quotation from a
Lama named Chang Chang
and this is a line of llamas similar to
the line of the D llamas called the
junas and uh they were very very close
to China they uh went to China they
taught in China One of the changa was
the
personal llama of one of the Emperors of
China and the author of this book
p uh it's said that he was actually one
of the
Changas but there were political
tensions at the time and his handlers
were afraid to uh declare him the
Incarnation of
CH so he was declared to be the
Incarnation of a of a rache of a of a
small Monastery called
P so pavona but but in his own biography
you can read that he he was always
attracted to Chinese objects like sedan
chairs and things like that and um that
he thought he himself he himself thought
he was
CH so anyway the Changas are really
extraordinary Lamas really really
extraordinary like yoga teachers to the
Emperor of China okay and here's a
quotation from
him from one of them
SHP
D this is tough okay it's really
hard there are there are those of Among
Us who have who are clear-minded
individuals but they get hung up on this
uh emptiness lingo okay The Emptiness
terminology they hear words like
self-standing or they heard words like
uh existing in reality okay Shen
they they miss the gas which are
appearing to them all the
time and then they go looking for them
in
books
okay he's being polite he says it would
appear to me that they are seeking a
gaka which has
horns and a tribe you know
even in Tibet to say they're looking for
a gaka that means horns means they're
looking for a a
devil they go looking for the
devil when when it's all around them all
the time okay they're looking for some
demonic
gcha as described in a in some heavy
philosophical
text and they're sitting on a chair
which is the gcha and they have fingers
which are Gan their own eyes are Gan
okay all right
sorry came
and dipd means uh dipd means
uh what do you call it you can't tell me
words anymore this is bad d means uh
J means a shadow or an obstacle gel
means has been ripped away so DP means
the revealed thing okay means the mother
meaning reality the the mother naked the
mother with the shadow ripped away is a
is a word in Buddhism for for emptiness
the mother of all things
uh covering her face like a veil
covering the mother's face like a veil
is the l l l came and is the are are all
the gachas around us all the time okay
so the way everything around us appears
all the time is veiling the beautiful
face of the mother which is emptiness
okay all right and they don't get it
okay they came and do means they don't
even they don't speak of that
and then they go off on explaining
emptiness in these long
lectures without getting to the point
they missed the point N means they don't
poke to the point all
right and I'm afraid the mother got away
I'm afraid the mother has has run from
them TR means
uh like to run from a a soldier or
something you know like to flee I'm
afraid the mother has fled from
them because they're looking for
emptiness in some heavy philosophical
books looking for the gaka in some heavy
philosophical books and they they're not
they don't
appreciate that it's appearing to them
all the time everything they see
everything they interact with every
person they've ever met every dish they
ever ate every poop they ever
pooped seem to be coming from its own
side and not from the seeds in their own
mind okay so they are surrounded they
are swimming in gas and they go looking
in some book for it you know and in the
time they take to go look in a book the
veiled mother has decided to leave the
room which means they missed emptiness
okay they didn't get get to emptiness
all
right
go we have a danger of ending up the
same
[Music]
way we'll stop there
okay what's a CH you can't say Chen
means an outer Aid
N means an inner Aid okay in Tantra the
outer Aid is your
partner uh and the inner Aid is your
meditations okay in in the open
teachings uh the outer Aid is the
instructions of your llama okay and the
inner Aid is sakang okay sakang is is an
important
principle sakang mean Sak means try to
do good karma new Good Karma Jung means
try to get rid of your old Bad Karma
okay so there are two supports or two
AIDS which will assist you in your
search for the gaka okay why is the G so
important if you can't
ident if you can't identify what
emptiness is empty of you'll never get
the emptiness so the first job is not to
perceive emptiness first job is to
perceive what it is that's Emptiness is
empty up the credit card that wasn't
there that that was a discovery card
anyway okay all right so
uh if you seek to see the gaka if you
seek to understand the gaka you're going
to need two two things outer Aid and an
inner Aid the outer Aid is your llama's
teaching that going to many teachings by
your llama
so a lot of llamas would say it would
take 3,000 hours of of these kinds of
teachings to get it okay uh it's like
flight time right I don't know but
anyway somebody's logging how many hours
you have in these kind of teachings okay
so that that's the outer
inside you have to keep trying to pile
up Good Karma and get rid of your Bad
Karma or you'll never get it you can sit
in the room with 10 other people and
nine 10 of them will get it and one
person won't okay and it's not that the
teaching was any different it's the same
words same teaching same text same llama
X number of people got it X number of
people fell
asleep okay the ones who fell
asleep have to suck J okay they have to
try to collect new Karma they have to
try to get rid of their old Bad Karma
okay then because that you could sit in
the room you can hear all the words you
can hear the same words in the same
language you can like the person saying
the words and just not get it okay if
you don't have enough Good Karma
so I think the cheapest dirtiest easiest
way to make good karma is rejoicing okay
like just think of people like his hoess
or people who are doing great things and
just be happy about them you know oh
those guys are all trying to do a free
Retreat I'm glad or all those Schmucks
went and built houses for a whole year
you know they're kind of dumb but anyway
no I mean they're all wrecks right uh
but they're kind of cool that was kind
of cool that they did that you know and
then you have to be happy about other
people's Good Deeds to me is the fastest
method of suck junp you know just just
be happy about other people who do cool
stuff and you get all these kic seeds
and you don't have to do anything except
be
happy and it means you don't have to go
to to buoy Arizona you know you can just
sit here and enjoy the weather and
uh and you collect you collect enough
Karma that the next time you come to a
talk you get it okay
it all
right I like that everybody is really
sick uh
because that's very
typical of an important event if
something is life-changing thing is
going to happen to you uh there will
come heavy heavy obstacles they will um
they will
Mass to people who are trying to have a
breakthrough you know they when you're
about to have a breakthrough then
there's massive interest in you from the
negative forces spirits and they'll do
anything they can to get you sick or or
like that you know because it's very
upsetting to them uh that they should
lose someone who believed in cars and
aspin for so long you know
okay uh so it's very very uh the quality
of the event or the retreat is often
judged by the number of obstacles
personal obstacles that plague the
people who attend so we're doing really
good I think from by that measure we we
got almost everybody sick
now uh I think the people who aren't
sick are going to start to feel
inadequate
uh but don't worry you'll catch
up okay but hang in
there and uh it's an honor to to attract
some attention of a demon usually we're
just doing what they want so they leave
us alone you know they're very happy
with your everyday Behavior so they
don't do anything they just let you do
it and then when you try to stick your
head up they they they see it you know
over 6 billion people oh
here's 160 or 70 who are trying to get
out of this mess and then they they like
they like all go wom you know like
thousands of them come to you and uh
make it
snow stuff like that okay
so you also created them right
okay uh have a good night take care